<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: turkey | Nathen Harvey]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/categories/turkey/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-29T23:52:55-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.nathenharvey.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathen Harvey]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[nathen@nathenharvey.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brine your turkey!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/11/21/brine-your-turkey/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-21T04:48:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/11/21/brine-your-turkey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's Thanksgiving week. That means it's time to start prepping your turkey.</p>

<p>In my opinion there are <strong>three very important things required for a terrific turkey</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>Start with a fresh turkey, I get mine from <a href="http://www.maplelawn.com/">Maple Lawn Farms</a>.</li>
<li>Brine the turkey (for 12-24 hours)</li>
<li>Once it's in the oven, leave it alone!</li>
</ol>


<p>I always prepare mine in an apple cider brine:</p>

<ul>
<li>8 cups apple cider</li>
<li>2/3 cup kosher salt</li>
<li>2/3 cup sugar</li>
<li>1 tablespoon black peppercorns, coarsely crushed</li>
<li>1 tablespoon whole allspice, coarsely crushed</li>
<li>8 (1/8-inch-thick) slices peeled fresh ginger</li>
<li>6 whole cloves</li>
<li>2 bay leaves</li>
<li>1 (12-pound) fresh or frozen turkey, thawed</li>
<li>2 oranges, quartered</li>
<li>6 cups ice</li>
</ul>


<p>Of course, this is for a 12-pound turkey, adjust for the size of your turkey.</p>

<h3>To prepare brine</h3>

<ul>
<li>combine first 8 ingredients in a large saucepan; bring to a boil.</li>
<li>Cook 5 minutes or until sugar and salt dissolve.</li>
<li>Cool completely.</li>
</ul>


<h3>To prepare the turkey</h3>

<ul>
<li>Remove giblets and neck from turkey.</li>
<li>Rinse turkey with cold water; pat dry.</li>
<li>Trim excess fat.</li>
<li>Stuff body cavity with orange quarters.</li>
</ul>


<p>You'll need something to to store the turkey in while it brines. Brine bags are relatively easy to find. They can be a bit messy to deal with so you might just use a large stockpot or a bucket. The important things are that the turkey is fully submersed in the brine and that you keep the whole thing cold throughout the process.</p>

<p>Place the turkey in the brine bag or other vessel of your choice and cover with the liquid. Place all of that into a cooler and fill with ice or place it into your refrigerator, if you have the room. Leave the turkey in the brine for 12-24 hours, turning occasionally.</p>

<h3>Cooking the turkey</h3>

<ul>
<li>Remove the turkey from the brine</li>
<li>Discard the brine and orange quarters</li>
<li>Rinse the turkey and pat it dry</li>
</ul>


<p>Cook the turkey as you normally would. I like to start it breast side down for the first 30 minutes at a higher temperature (475&ordm; - 500&ordm;) then flip it over and reduce the heat to 350&ordm; for the remainder. If possible, use a <a href="http://www.williams-sonoma.com/products/digital-voice-alert-thermometer/?pkey=x%7C4%7C1%7C%7C4%7Cmeat%20thermometer%7C%7C0&amp;cm_src=OLDLINK">leave-in thermometer</a> so that you don't have to continually open the oven to check the temperature of the turkey.</p>

<p>Once the turkey is done cooking, be sure to let it rest at least 20 minutes before carving.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
