<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: DevOps DC | Nathen Harvey]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/categories/devops-dc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-01-02T17:21:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.nathenharvey.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathen Harvey]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[nathen@nathenharvey.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MongoDB Community Awards]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/29/mongodb-community-awards/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-29T23:54:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/29/mongodb-community-awards</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During this year's <a href="http://www.10gen.com/events/mongosv-2011">MongoSV</a>, <a href="http://10gen.com">10gen</a> presented awards to peer-nominated community members for their contributions to the MongoDB project.</p>

<p>There were <a href="http://blog.10gen.com/post/12290733213/mongodb-community-awards-to-be-presented-at-mongosv">3 different categories</a>:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Innovative Application Award</strong> - recognizes a company or individual who has built an innovative application using MongoDB.</li>
<li><strong>Core Contributor Award</strong> - recognizes a community member for significant contribution to the codebase of the MongoDB core server, language drivers, or tools.</li>
<li><strong>Community Champion Award</strong> - recognizes an individual for their efforts evangelizing and growing the MongoDB community.</li>
</ol>


<p>This is the first year that 10gen has organized these awards. I think they're a great way to recognize the contributions made by a few members of the community. I hope a significant portion of people in the community took the time to nominate or vote for another individual.  I suspect more community members will participate and 10gen will do a more to advertise the program in years to come.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Community Champion Award</h2>

<p>I was honored to be selected as a <a href="http://blog.10gen.com/post/13835130448/voting-open-for-the-mongodb-community-awards-winners">finalist in the Community Champion category</a>. As a co-organizer for both the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Washington-DC-MongoDB-Users-Group/">Washington DC MongoDB User Group</a> and <a href="http://www.meetup.com/DevOpsDC/">DevOps DC</a>, I work to bring together people who are interested in MongoDB and other great technologies. We've grown the MongoDB group to over 250 members through consistent meetings, detailed event summaries, and good beer.</p>

<h2>I'm going to SXSW Interactive!</h2>

<p><img class="right" src="http://nathenharvey.s3-website-us-east-1.amazonaws.com/blog/images/sxsw_interactive.png" width="352" height="169" title="SXSW Interactive" alt="SXSW Interactive"></p>

<p>Shortly before the voting was opened to the public, 10gen announced the <a href="http://blog.10gen.com/post/12838656615/mongodb-community-awards-grand-prize-announcement">grand prize</a>:  a trip to <a href="http://sxsw.com/interactive">South By Southwest Interactive</a>. The nomination and being selected as a finalist were a great recognition of my effort and accomplishments. However, I've always wanted to got to SXSW.  Once I found out this was the prize, I was really excited at the possibility of winning the award!</p>

<p>As I reviewed the finalists, I was pretty certain I wouldn't be selected as the winner. Everyone on the list has made some incredible contributions to the community.</p>

<p>At the end of MongoSV the <a href="http://blog.10gen.com/post/14278640986/announcing-the-2011-mongodb-community-award-winners">winners were announced</a>. It was quite a surprise to find out I'd been selected as the winner in the Community Champion category! This was the perfect end to a great two days for me which included the <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/29/mongodb-masters/">MongoDB Masters Summit</a> and <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/29/mongosv/">presenting at the conference</a>.</p>

<h2>Thanks!</h2>

<p>A heartfelt <strong>THANK YOU</strong> is in order for all of the members of the <strong>MongoDC</strong> group who nominated and voted for me, for <strong>10gen</strong> for organizing the contest and awards, and my <strong>colleagues, friends, and family</strong> who 'rocked the vote'!</p>

<p>I'm looking forward to meeting up with the other Community Award winners in Austin!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Agenda Tips for a Tech User Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/agenda-tips-for-a-tech-user-group/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-13T19:53:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/agenda-tips-for-a-tech-user-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/tips-for-hosting-a-tech-user-group/">previous post</a>, I gave some <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/tips-for-hosting-a-tech-user-group/">ideas about how to run a successful user group meeting</a>. In this post, I'll focus on the actual meeting format we typically use for our <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Washington-DC-MongoDB-Users-Group/">Washington DC MongoDB Users Group</a>. You may find that this format works well for any technical user group.</p>

<p>We've experimented with a couple of different formats but I think we've settled into something that generally works for us. Some of these don't work with a meeting that's larger than 20 people; adjust accordingly.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Sign-in sheets</h3>

<p>I usually include a sign-in sheet for our meetings. The sheets usually include space for name, email address, twitter handle, and a space for the attendee to write in a question or topic they'd like to discuss when we have some an open discussion. Usually attendees are already on members on <a href="http://www.meetup.com/">Meetup.com</a> so it's easy enough to reach out to them but this provides another way to capture their contact info.</p>

<h3>Introductions and Announcements</h3>

<p>We start the meeting by going around the room and asking everyone to introduce themselves and share any announcements they may have. The announcements might be that they're hiring, looking for work, or something about an application or open source contribution they've made.</p>

<h3>Meeting content</h3>

<p>After the introductions, you get into the meat of the meeting. This can take on many different formats here are some that we've used successfully:</p>

<h4>Demos &amp; Tutorials</h4>

<p>Having someone demo a product or application that they've built always goes over well. In some instances, we've had people build applications on-the-fly to give attendees an idea of how easy it can be to work with <a href="http://www.mongodb.org/">MongoDB</a>.</p>

<h4>Lightning Talks</h4>

<p>4-6 attendees give 5-10 minute talks on a given subject related to MongoDB. This is a great way for the attendees to share something they're passionate about and practice their presentation skills.</p>

<h4>"Un-meeting"</h4>

<p>During an un-meeting, participants propose talks or discussion items and that drives the agenda for the meeting. I try to leave time for this sort of attendee-driven agenda in every meeting, even when we have scheduled presenters.</p>

<h4>Presentations</h4>

<p>It's great to line-up one or two speakers for the meeting. I think the best combination of speakers for a MongoDB meeting is to have one "intro" talk and one that is more advanced. We always seem to have a number of attendees who have done very little, if anything, with MongoDB prior to the meeting. Having an introductory presentation is great for them. The more advanced talk may get into replication, sharding, or production operations.</p>

<h3>Picks, tips, and #protips</h3>

<p>I stole this idea from the <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/">Ruby Rogues podcast</a>. At the end of each meeting we go around the room and ask each attendee to share a pick, tip, or #protip. These can be related to MongoDB but don't have to be. Heck, they don't need to be related to tech at all. Just something that the attendee has been using, doing, or has learned recently that he'd like to share with the group. Tips have included emacs and vi tips, command line tips, books, games, and even <a href="http://www.wikihow.com/Suppress-the-Gag-Reflex">tips on how to suppress the gag reflex</a>.</p>

<h3>Announce the next meetup</h3>

<p>It's key to announce the next meetup at the end of the current one. Minimally, you'll want to announce the date, time, and location. Preferably, you'll also be able to announce the theme of the night or the actual speakers.</p>

<h3>Other ideas</h3>

<p>Lately, I've been kicking around the idea of a book club meeting. The idea is that we'd pick a book, maybe <a href="http://www.manning.com/banker/">MongoDB in Action</a> and build a couple of the meeting agendas around chapters from the book. For example, perhaps we'd look at Part 1 Getting started in February, Part 2 - Application development in March, and Part 3 - MongoDB mastery in April. We may even be able to spend an entire meeting on the content and theme of a single chapter. The group could publish reviews of each section as they go. Have you had any experience with a user group that's done this?</p>

<p>We've also used Skype to bring experts in to present virtually. I've found that this works best when the presenter has a brief (15 minute) presentation and then is available for Q &amp; A.</p>

<p>For some more great suggestions, including suggestions on how to get great presenters, check out <a href="https://twitter.com/cwestin63">Chris Westin's</a> blog post - <a href="https://www.bookofbrilliantthings.com/blog/how-to-run-a-successful-tech-meetup">How to Run a Successful Tech Meetup</a>.</p>

<p>What suggestions do you have? Please leave a comment or get in touch with me.</p>

<p>Also, checkout my <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/tips-for-hosting-a-tech-user-group/">previous post</a> where I gave some <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/tips-for-hosting-a-tech-user-group/">ideas about how to run a successful user group meeting</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips for Hosting a Tech User Group]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/tips-for-hosting-a-tech-user-group/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-13T19:24:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/tips-for-hosting-a-tech-user-group</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In January of 2011, I started hosting a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Washington-DC-MongoDB-Users-Group/">monthly MongoDB meetup</a>. My employer, <a href="http://www.customink.com/">CustomInk</a>, was looking for ways to become better known in the local DC technology market. We were also just getting started with our initial production deployment of MonogoDB. Having engineers from the area come to our office, get to know CustomInk, and share their experiences with using MongoDB was a great opportunity!</p>

<p>Before I get much further, I'd like to give a hat tip to those user groups and podcasts that I learned from and stole ideas from. Namely, <a href="http://www.meetup.com/dcruby/">DC RUG</a>, <a href="http://www.meetup.com/bmore-on-rails/">B'more on Rails group</a>, and the <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/">Ruby Rogues podcast</a>.</p>

<p>Having a good space for hosting these types of meetings is important. CustomInk has two different spaces that we can utilize. The Parlour is a very cozy sitting room that includes a fireplace. It's suitable for a groups of up to 30 people. The Cafe is quite a bit larger, we can host up to 80 people there. We also have a very nice outdoor patio which could hold 80 people but planning weather-dependent meetings doesn't feel like the right way to go. The patio is connected to both the Parlour and the Cafe so networking at the beginning of the meeting sometimes happens there.</p>

<p>Our success hosting the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Washington-DC-MongoDB-Users-Group/">MongoDB User Group</a> has led to us hosting a number of other meetups. We are the regular host for the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/DevOpsDC/">DevOps DC</a> meetup and have hosted events for <a href="http://www.meetup.com/ncagtug/events/17035395/">Android application development</a>, <a href="http://www.meetup.com/R-users-DC/events/37862562/">R user group</a>, <a href="http://www.meetup.com/NoVa-Javascript-Ext-JS-Users-Group/events/36841452/">JavaScript user group</a>, and a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/TwitterTeaTimeDC/events/38265862/">Twitter API meetup</a>.</p>

<p>The MongoDB group now includes over 250 members and the DevOps DC group is over 100. Based on our experience, I believe there are a number of things that you can do to grow and run a successful meetup group.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Consistent date, time, location</h3>

<p>Having a consistent date, time, and location may be one of the most important things you can do. This allows members to plan their schedule and their commute. Finding the location of any meetup can be an anxiety-filled experience for some people. Is this the right building? Which floor is this meeting on? There's comfort in knowing that next month's meeting will happen in the same space as this month's. You may feel it would be better to alternate locations. We've certainly had some requests for this in the groups we regularly host. Based on feedback from other groups and some of our own experience, this is a bad idea. We've seen or heard of too many members missing meetings because they went to the "other" location. For the MongoDB group, we meet on the third Wednesday of the month at 6:30. Pick a day and time that works best for you and stick with it.</p>

<p>A location that is easily accessible via public transportation is certainly desirable but may not always be feasible.</p>

<h3>Encourage member participation</h3>

<p>Once you've got everyone at your meetup it's important that you make this a warm, welcoming place where members feel comfortable and are encouraged to participate. We ask attendees to introduce themselves, share a pick, and contribute during open discussions.</p>

<h3>Register a twitter account</h3>

<p>A twitter handle that matches your group is a great way to help promote your meetings and encourage attendance. I use <a href="http://twitter.com/mongodc">@MongoDC</a> and will frequently tweet about topics that our members are interested in. Of course, the primary use of the account is to announce upcoming meetings and speakers. However, I also use it for sharing MongoDB related news such as <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/MongoDC/status/113307839249907713">product releases</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/MongoDC/status/135041129455427584">upcoming conferences</a>. Additionally, we ask our members to share their twitter handle when they arrive. This allows me to put together a <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/MongoDC/mongodc-16-nov-2011/members">Twitter list</a> of the people who attended (an idea I stole from the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/bmore-on-rails/">B'more on Rails group</a>).</p>

<h3>Feed the group</h3>

<p>You're probably scheduling your meetings right around the same time that most people would otherwise be eating dinner. CustomInk provides pizza, sodas, and beer for each meetup. Personally, I'm a bit of a beer lover so try to provide a unique offering at each meeting. This a good sponsorship opportunity for companies interested in reaching your group, too.</p>

<h3>Give away FREE stuff</h3>

<p>What's a user group meeting without some sort of free swag? <a href="http://www.10gen.com/">10gen</a>, the company behind MongoDB, is great about making sure I always have something to give away at the meetings. Quick reference cards, stickers, and coffee mugs are usually in ample supply. Occasionally, we'll have a books, conference tickets or discounts, or other special swag that we can giveaway, too.</p>

<h3>Wifi</h3>

<p>Provide free wifi to your attendees. It's frustrating to go to a technical meeting without wifi.</p>

<h3>Leverage Meetup.com</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.meetup.com/">Meetup.com</a> has a lot of great tools to help you organize meetings, communicate with individual members or with the entire group, and more. Be sure to checkout the "Organizer Tips" available under the "Group Tools" menu. Create a presence on Facebook, LinkedIn, Twitter, or anywhere else your members or potential members are going to be but always link back to the group's page on meetup.com. Use the meetup site to post any presentations from your meetings. I also find it's very helpful to <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Washington-DC-MongoDB-Users-Group/pages/November_Meetup_Recap/">summarize your meetings on the site</a>. This gives attendees easy access to everything that happened and gives new members an idea about the content and quality of the meetings.</p>

<p>It might also be interesting to have a page on the Meetup site where your members can highlight their own open source contributions. Perhaps they've contributed to a MongoDB driver?</p>

<p>There are other sites that offer similar functionality to Meetup.com but I firmly believe Meetup.com is the best. It's where many people go to look for interesting groups and the tools they provide are great.</p>

<h3>Other ideas</h3>

<p>Lately, I've been kicking around the idea of having a group library. Members and publisher could contribute books that the group might be interested in. Each book could be "borrowed" for up to a month. Have you had any experience with a user group that's done this?</p>

<p>For some more great suggestions, including suggestions on how to get great presenters, check out <a href="https://twitter.com/cwestin63">Chris Westin's</a> blog post - <a href="https://www.bookofbrilliantthings.com/blog/how-to-run-a-successful-tech-meetup">How to Run a Successful Tech Meetup</a>.</p>

<p>What suggestions do you have? Please leave a comment or get in touch with me.</p>

<p>In my <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/agenda-tips-for-a-tech-user-group/">next post</a>, I'll provide <a href="http://nathenharvey.com/blog/2011/12/13/agenda-tips-for-a-tech-user-group/">some suggestions on the agenda / format for each meeting</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
